A Guide to the Small Business Development Center Records, 1980-2004: UA 0009
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Small Business Development Center Records,
1980-2004
Special Collections, James Madison University
JMU Small Business Development Center
Virginia SBDC Shenandoah Valley
UA 0009
2.48 cubic feet; 8 boxes
The Small Business Development Center Records documents the creation and growth of the Shenandoah Valley Small Business Development Center. The collection comprises of financial budgets, proposals, donations, outreach programs, and articles that cover the growing success of the Shenandoah Valley SBDC at James Madison University.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Given to JMU Special Collections by Rosie Riggleman, Office Manager of the Shenandoah Valley SBDC, in April 2014.
Admin History
The Shenandoah Valley Small Business Development Center (SBDC) was established in 1989 at James Madison University. Originally named the James Madison University SBDC, the Center for Entrepreneurship in the College of Business established the center as a satellite office in 1987 in order to support the success of local businesses based on the Center's programming. In 2002, the James Madison University SBDC became the Shenandoah Valley SBDC when a new office was opened at Blue Ridge Community College. Today, The Shenandoah Valley SBDC is a not-for profit partnership between JMU, the US Small Business Administration, and the cities and counties in their service region. It is currently one of 29 centers throughout Virginia. The mission of the Shenandoah Valley SBDC is to advise, train, and inform small business in order to help them achieve success by offering consulting services to new and established businesses. Their region covers the counties of Augusta, Bath, Highland, Page, Rockbridge, Rockingham, and Shenandoah as well as the major cities located within these counties.
The nationwide Small Business Development Center (SBDC) focuses on client education and is the federal government's largest and most successful management and technical assistance program for small businesses. In the 1940s Congress was first introduced to the idea of establishing a university-based business extension service. By 1953 the Small Business Administration was established. This reflected the federal government's recognition of the need for small businesses within the economy. Advancements for the Small Business Administration continued when President Carter signed the Small Business Development Center Act into law in 1980. This program strove to nationally help and support the development and operation of small businesses by providing them with management development, technical information, product planning and development, and domestic and international market development. In addition, the program assists established businesses as well as aspiring entrepreneurs. Virginia was added into this network during the years 1988-1990; by 1991 every state in the country was involved in the Small Business Development Center program.
Scope and Content
This collection covers the years 1980-2004 for the Shenandoah Valley SBDC. The records document financial information, proposals, meeting minutes, correspondence, journals, photographs, articles, annual reports, and pamphlets from various colleges. The collection is arranged into four series.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in four series: Series 1: Financial Records, 1980-1999 Series 2: JMU SBDC Planning and Development, 1986-2003
Subseries 1: Proposals, 1986-2003,
Subseries 2: Annual Reports, 1984-2003 Series 3: Subject Files, 1982-2004 Series 4: Digital Media and Slides, 1987-2003
Bibliography
James Madison University. "Small Business Development Center." jmu.edu. https://www.jmu.edu/cob/centers/sbdc/index.shtml. Accessed May 24, 2018.
Virginia SBDC Shenandoah Valley. "About Us." valleysbdc.org. http://www.valleysbdc.org/about/. Accessed May 24, 2018.
U.S. Small Business Administration. "Small Business Development Center." sba.gov. https://www.sba.gov/tools/local-assistance/sbdc. Accessed May 24, 2018.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Small business -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg -- Planning; Small business -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg -- Management; Small business -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg -- Finance; Community development -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg
Genre and Form Terms:
Financial Records; Annual reports; Proposals; Photographs; Floppy Discs; Serials (publications)
- Financial Records, 1980-1999
  Scope and Content
  Arranged chronologically.
  Series 1: Financial Records, 1980-1999 contains information and documents pertaining to the financial status of the Shenandoah Valley Small Business Development Center. It contains proposals, grants, contracts, and budgets, including the original proposal to establish the Center.
  - Requests for Petty Cash, 1980, 1990-1992 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Access Restrictions
    Privacy protected information may be revealed during use of this file. Researchers agree to make no notes or other recordation of privacy protected information found within this file, and further agree not to publish or disclose such information for any purpose.
  - Center for Entrepreneurship Course Proposal Information, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - CIT 50,000 Funding, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Original" 50,000 Proposal, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - February 1988 to January 31, 1989 CIT $50,000, 1988-1999 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Requisitions and DPO's, 1988-1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Account #14408 Foundation Account, 1989-1990 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - SBDC Recovery-1st Contract, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Funkhouser Entrepreneurship Research B14408, 1989-1991 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - F.E.R.F. Par Forms, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - SBDC Miscellaneous Financial Documents, 1990-1991, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1991 Deposits/Financials, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Center for Entrepreneurship, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Romanian Grant Proposal, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - JMU SBDC Budget (Folder 1 of 3), 1999 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - JMU SBDC Budget (Folder 2 of 3), 1999 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - JMU SBDC Budget (Folder 3 of 3), 1999 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- JMU SBDC Planning and Development, 1982-2003
  Arranged in two subseries: Proposals, 1986-2003 and Annual Reports, 1984-2003. Arranged chronologically with each series.
  Series 2: JMU SBDC Planning and Development, 1982-2003 contains records documenting the establishment of the James Madison University SBDC and its development into the Shenandoah Valley SBDC. The Proposal subseries contains proposals for funding and projects as well as the 1998 strategic plan for the JMU SBDC. The Annual Report subseries includes annual and quarterly reports from the JMU SBDC, the Shenandoah Valley SBDC, and the Virginia SBDC. Reports from 1993, 1995, 1996, and 2000 are not included.
  - Proposals, 1986-2003
    - Proposals to Assist the Center for Innovative Technology, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Center for Entrepreneurship Proposal for Funding, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Project Proposal for the Center for Entrepreneurship (Folder 1 of 2), 1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Project Proposal for the Center for Entrepreneurship (Folder 2 of 2), 1987 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Center for Innovative Technology Project Proposal, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Proposal for Business Development Center (Folder 1 of 2), 1987 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Proposal for Business Development Center (Folder 2 of 2), 1987 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Proposal for JMU Entrepreneurship Program, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Proposal for Renewal Funding for Center for Innovative Technology Entrepreneurship Program, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Proposal for a Small Business Assistance Center, December 1, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Proposal for Small Business Assistance Centers, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Application for Federal Assistance, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Proposal to the U.S. Small Business Administration for the Continued Operation of the VA SBDC, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous Items Concerning the 1991 Report, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous Papers Concerning the Report of 1992, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Proposal to the U.S. Small Business Administration and Budget Information, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - SBDC Proposal, Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1984-2003
    - Reports, 1984, 1985, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Final Report, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - First Report for Appalachian Business Development Center, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - ARC Final Report, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Business Development Center Model for Rural Economic Development Final Report, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - CIT Final Report Draft, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - CIT Final Report, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Final Report to the Center for Innovative Technology, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - CIT Final Report, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - JMU SBDC Annual Report, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - JMU SBDC First Quarter Report, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - JMU SBDC Second Quarter Report, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - JMU SBDC Third Quarter Report, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - JMU SBDC Annual Report, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - VA SBDC Annual Report, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - JMU SBDC First Quarter Report, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - JMU SBDC Second Quarter Report, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - JMU SBDC Third Quarter Report, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - JMU SBDC Annual Report, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - JMU SBDC First Quarter Report, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - JMU SBDC Second Quarter Report, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - JMU SBDC Third Quarter Report, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - VSBDC Annual Report, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - VSBDC Annual Report, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Virginia SBDC Annual Report, 1998, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - JMU SBDC Annual Report, January 1-December 31, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - JMU SBDC Annual Report, July 1-December 31, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Shenandoah Valley Small Business Development Center Annual Report, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - VSBDC Financial Audit, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - SBDC Summary Annual ReportSBDC Summary Annual ReportSBDC Summary Annual ReportSBDC Summary Annual ReportSBDC Summary Annual ReportSBDC Summary Annual ReportSBDC Summary Annual ReportSBDC Summary Annual ReportSBDC Summary Annual ReportSBDC Summary Annual ReportSBDC Summary Annual Report, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Subject Files, 1982-2004
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Series 3: Subject Files, 1982-2004 contains documents and copies of articles and correspondence that have been published to promote or explain the SBDC program. This series contains news articles from JMU Entrepnews, photographs of professors, including Professor Moody, and others involved with the JMU SBDC as well as booklets that explain the steps necessary to start a business. Budget and audit information, along with reviews and evaluations are included as well.
  - ARC Xeroxing, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Binder of Articles and Photographs of the SBDC, 1989-1992 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence and Articles Promoting SBDC Programs, 1998, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Duplicates, 1980-2004 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Entrepreneurship Task Force and Correspondence with Baylor University, 1982-1984 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - How to Start a New Business in Harrisonburg and Rockingham County, Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Interim Report to Appalachian Regional Commission, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - JMU Entreprenews Articles, 1986-1992 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - JMU SBDC Counseling Evaluation, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Legal Considerations for Starting a Business, October 2, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Memorandum of Agreement Between Virginia Department of Economic Development for VSBDC, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Articles about SBDC, 1987-1989, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Budget/Financial Information on SBDC, 1987-1991 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Documents and Articles Concerning SBDC, 1989,1990, 1996,1997, Undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - New Contract, 1990-1991 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Photographs of SBDC, 2004, Undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - OMC Related Documents, 1986, 1988, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Photographs, (Folder 1 of 2), Undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Photographs, (Folder 2 of 2), Undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Moody and Brochure, Undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Report of the Joint Legislation, Audit and Review Commission on Review of Economic Development in VA, (Folder 1 of 2), 1991 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Report of the Joint Legislation, Audit and Review Commission on Review of Economic Development in VA, (Folder 2 of 2), 1991 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - SBDC Program Announcement, March, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - SBDC Sub-Center on Site Reviews, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Small Business Develop. Center Policy Guidelines, August, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - The Inception and Development of a Business Development Center, Manual, (Folder 1 of 2), 1987 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - The Inception and Development of a Business Development Center, Manual, (Folder 2 of 2), 1987 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Transparencies, Undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Digital Media and Slides, 1987-2003
  Series 4: Digital Media and Slides, 1987-2003 contains a floppy disk containing information concerning the SBDC and a folder of photograph negatives of the Center for Entrepreneurship staff.
  - Correspondence and Articles Promoting SBDC, 1998, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Entrepreneurship Staff, July 29, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 12)